Guide to the Alvin P. Shapiro Papers, 1942-1998 UA.90.F64
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Alvin P. Shapiro Papers
1942-1998
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Shapiro, Alvin P. (Alvin Philip)
UA.90.F64
8 Linear Feet (7 boxes)
Alvin P. Shapiro, a faculty member at the University of Pittsburgh's medical school (1956-1998), concentrated his research on hypertension, clinical pharmacology, and psychosomatic response with particular focus on the links between hypertension and stress, as well as renal function and hypertension related to systemic scleroderma. He was very active in the administration of the University of Pittsburgh's Medical School as well as Presbyterian University Hospital. Notably, he headed the study section of the Hypertension Detection and Follow-up Program, which produced the first large-scale study of hypertension. Included in this collection are published and unpublished abstracts and manuscripts, research study data sheets, discussion and presentation materials, book drafts, personal military records, personal and professional correspondence, and a few photographs.
Arrangement
The Shapiro papers have been arranged into the following series. Extensive scope notes on each series are available in the container list.
Series I. Unpublished Abstracts and Manuscripts
Series II. Publications from Committees, Groups and Panels
Series III. Published Abstracts and Discussions
Series IV. Published Manuscripts
Series V. Book Drafts and Materials
Series VI. Personal Papers
Series VII. Photographs
Previous Citation
Alvin P. Shapiro Papers, 1942-1998, UA.90.F64, University Archives, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Biography
Alvin P. Shapiro was born on December 28, 1920 in Nashville, Tennessee, but grew up on Staten Island in New York. Throughout his career, he contributed significantly to the practice of internal medicine with his extensive research on hypertension and psychosomatic medical issues. Shapiro earned his medical degree from the Long Island College of Medicine in 1944, and spent his residency at the Goldwater Memorial Hospital in New York where he specialized in internal medicine. He then served as a captain in the U.S. Army Medical Corps and was stationed at the Army Air Base in Adak, Alaska.
After military service, Shapiro was employed as an instructor and researcher in the Department of Internal Medicine at the University of Cincinnati College of Medicine, and later at the Southwestern Medical School in Dallas, Texas. He joined the staff of the University of Pittsburgh's Medical School in 1956, and was an active researcher and author until his death in 1998. At the University of Pittsburgh, he was the director of the psychosomatic program and chief of the clinical pharmacology/hypertension section from 1960-1971. He was the associate dean for academic affairs at the University's medical school from 1971-1975, vice chairman of the department of medicine from 1975-1979, chief of Presbyterian University Hospital from 1977-1979, and chairman of the credentials committee from 1980-1986. From 1986-1993 he was the director of the internal medicine training program at Shadyside Hospital.
Shapiro's research focused on hypertension, clinical pharmacology, and psychosomatic response, with a particular focus on the links between hypertension and stress, as well as renal function and hypertension related to systemic scleroderma. He headed the study section of the Hypertension Detection and Follow-up Program at UPMC, which, in the late 1970s, produced the first large-scale study in which men and women of diverse racial backgrounds were given a simple outpatient therapy for the treatment of hypertension. The initial paper that resulted from this study is considered a landmark in the field by the Journal of the American Medical Association.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Ruth Shapiro in May 1999.
Scope and Content Notes
The Alvin P. Shapiro Papers document the pursuit of medical research into the causes and treatment of hypertension. Shapiro was an active physician and medical researcher from his time in the U.S. Army in the late 1940s through his tenure at the University of Pittsburgh's medical school, which ended upon his death in the late 1990s. His papers include research data as well as published and unpublished abstracts, discussions, and manuscript materials, through which changes in theories and research processes can be seen. The development of hypertension research is notably evident when examining draft revisions of articles and peer-review comments from submissions to scholarly medical journals. Shapiro's work focused predominantly on how stress and other psychosomatic factors can affect blood pressure and also examinations of renal function and hypertension related to systemic scleroderma. The evolution, efficacy, and side effects of treatments for hypertension, including pharmacologic and non-pharmacologic treatments, are also prominent themes in this collection.
His role as a medical educator also shaped Shapiro's research interests. This collection includes scholarly works that examine and critique medical education in the United States in the 1970s. There are also many pieces, generally written for local Pittsburgh medical community newsletters, in which Shapiro reflects on his personal experiences as a doctor, researcher, educator, and patient. Shapiro's time as a military physician during World War II is also represented.
Conspicuously missing from the Shapiro Papers are published manuscript materials from his early career - from the 1950s through 1970. It is unclear why these documents are not a part of this collection. There are, however, unpublished materials, and materials related to published abstracts and discussions from this time period.
Access Restrictions
Several files in this collection have been restricted because they contain the names and medical information of human study subjects. Restricted folders are identified in the contents list and are contained in Boxes 1-6. For questions about access conditions, contact the University Archivist.
Hypertension -- Treatment; Hypertension -- Causes and theories of causation; Medicine and psychology; Medicine, Psychosomatic; Hypertension -- Prevention; Systemic scleroderma; Health and medicine; Medical education -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Physicians -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Medical teaching personnel -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Pyelonephritis; Kidneys -- Diseases; University of Pittsburgh; Faculty papers; Hypertension -- Research; Hypertension -- Psychosomatic aspects; United States. Army. Medical Corps; Presbyterian-University Hospital of Pittsburgh; Shadyside Hospital (Pittsburgh, Pa.); University of Pittsburgh. School of Medicine -- Faculty; Shapiro, Alvin P. (Alvin Philip)
- Unpublished Abstracts and Manuscripts, 1954-1992; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This section contains abstracts and manuscript draft materials that were submitted for publication in scholarly medical journals, or for inclusion in medical conferences, but were not accepted. Frequently included are letters from journal editors and peer reviewers that explain why certain submissions were rejected, or offer suggestions for revisions. When taken together with Shapiro's published materials, this section helps to provide a more complete perspective on the evolution of hypertension research and publication. Documents are arranged chronologically.
  Access Restrictions
  Some files in this section include the personal and medical information of human study subjects and access is governed by certain restrictions. In Box 1, Folders 4 and 16 are restricted.
  - Unpublished Abstracts, 1960-1992 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Effect of Low Sodium on Body Fluid Distribution in Hypertension, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Effect of Low Sodium on Body Fluid Distribution in Hypertension [RESTRICTED], 1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Blood Pressure of Unanesthetized Cats, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Drug Therapy of Hypertension, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - ACHT in Pepsinogen (Gastroenterology Research Group), 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Effect of ACHT on Urine, Blood and Gastric Pepsinogen in the Rat, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Pepsinogen Paper, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Susceptibility of Rats with Renal Hypertension to Experimental Pyelonephritis, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - The Effect of Lysergic Acid Diethylamide (LSD-25) on Learning in Rats, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Failure of Production Teratogenic by Chlorothiazide in Rats, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Clyde Mood Scale Measurements on Fraternal and Identical Twins Subjected to Noxious Stimuli, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Studies of the Role of Antibiotic Persistence in the Therapy of Experimental Pyelonephritis II., 1969 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Effect of the Release of Mechanical Compression to the Hindbrain by Vascular Structures on the Systemic Blood Pressure and Related Parameters in Normotensive and Hypertensive Man, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Effect of the Release of Mechanical Compression to the Hindbrain by Vascular Structures on the Systemic Blood Pressure and Related Parameters in Normotensive and Hypertensive Man [RESTRICTED], 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Angiotensin II-Induced Proteinuria: A Study of the Relative Effects of Elevated Blood Pressure and Altered Glomerular Permeability, 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Biobehavioral Approaches to the Treatment of Hypertension, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Chapter for Leonard White for "Placebo: Clinical Phenomena and New Insights", 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - New Onset of Hypertension Following Cardiac Transplantation: A Preliminary Report and Analysis, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Chapter for "Handbook of Prevention", 1984 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Quality of Life Issues in Hypertension and Antihypertensive Therapy, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Microvascular Decompression of the Medulla in Hypertension, 1985-1988 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Reflections on Clinical Education and the Doctor of Tomorrow, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Neuropsychological Consequences of Hypertension and Its Treatment, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Relationship of Mild Diastolic Hypertension to Memory Performance, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Publications from Committees, Groups, and Panels, 1979-1986; II.
  Shapiro participated in multiple committees, panels, and group research studies related to hypertension. Most of the material in this series focuses on the links between stress and hypertension, stress and illness, and non-pharmacologic treatments for hypertension. Also included are three publications that resulted from the Hypertension Detection and Follow-up Program: a groundbreaking long-term study that was conducted at the University of Pittsburgh's medical school; it was one of the first to broadly compare instances and treatment of hypertension across gender and racial categories. The bulk of material in this series consists of copies of the published articles and transcripts of discussions, however some related correspondence and draft materials are present. Documents are arranged chronologically.
  - The Role of Stress in Hypertension, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Stress and Physical Illness, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Hypertension Detection and Follow-up Group, 1979-1984 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - The 1984 Report of the Joint National Committee on Detection, Evaluation, and Treatment of High Blood Pressure (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Nonpharmacological Approaches to the Control of High Blood Pressure, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Report on Fully Automated Blood Pressure Monitoring, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Published Abstracts and Discussions, 1950-1997; III.
  This series includes published abstracts, discussions, and presentations, as well as relating research study data sheets, notes, graphs, correspondence, and publication submission forms from the whole of Shapiro's professional life. Shapiro was interested in the medical issues surrounding hypertension and its treatment from very early in his career, and the documents in this series most fully illustrate the evolution of hypertension research from the 1950s through the 1990s. Many of the early materials in this series document early research and testing that link stress to increased instances of hypertension and other medical problems, particularly issues related to renal function and pyelonephritis. Later documents focus largely on the efficacy of non-pharmacologic treatments for hypertension and hypertension related to scleroderma. Also included in this section are published book reviews and letters to the editor. Documents are arranged chronologically.
  Some files in this section include the personal and medical information of human study subjects and access is governed by certain restrictions. In Box 2, Folders 28, 42, and 94 are restricted.
  - Partial Curriculum Vitae of Abstracts and Discussions, 1950-1962 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - The Effect of Sodium Intake on the Action of ACTH in Uncomplicated Essential Hypertension, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Physiologic and Pharmacologic Studies in a Case of Pheochromocytoma, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - A Comparative Study of the Effects of Veratrum Viride on Hypertensive and Normotensive Subjects, [1951] (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - A Comparative Evaluation of the Effectiveness of Several New Hypotensive Agents as Determined by their Action in Experimental Renal Hypertension and in the Human Patient, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - A Critical Evaluation of the Hypotensive Action of Hydralazine and Hexamethonium Salts in Human and Experimental Hypertension, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - The Influence of Emotional Variables in the Evaluation of Hypotensive Agents, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Relationship of Adrenalin and T Wave Inversion in the Anxiety State, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Effect of Low Sodium Intake on Body Fluid Distribution in Hypertension, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - The Volume of the Fluid Compartments in Human and Experimental Hypertension, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Effect of Behavioral Disturbance on Blood Pressure of Cats, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - The Pathogenesis of Hematogenous Pyelonephritis in Rats and Its Production by a Simple New Method, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Experimental Chronic Pyelonephritis in the Rat, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Effect of Behavioral Disturbances on Blood Pressure and Related Function in the Rat, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - The Relationship of Bacterial Species to the Pathogenesis of Hematogenous Pyelonephritis, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Factors Influencing Development of Hypertensive Vascular Disease in Rats with Renal Injury, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Relationships of Hypertension and Renal Impairment to Experimental Chronic Pyelonephritis in Rats, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Toxicity of Proteus Urease, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Relationships of Hypertension and Experimental Pyelonephritis in the Rat, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Hypertension and Pyelonephritis in the Rat, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Discussion (III The Renal Lesion in Pyelonephritis), 1956-1960 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Effect of Hypotensive Drugs on the Pressor Response to Noxious Stimuli, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Presented at Montreal, March 1960 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Comparative Studies of the Blood Pressure Responses to Different Noxious Stimuli, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Susceptibility of Renal Hypertensive Rats to Pyelonephritis and the Predisposition of Pyelonephritic Rats to Hypertension, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Use of Catalase Test to Detect Renal Infection in Hypertension, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Increased Susceptibility to Pyelonephritis During Acute Hypertension by Angiotensin, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Pressor Response to Noxious Stimuli in Hypertensive Patients: Effect of Reserpine and Chlorothiazide, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Increased Susceptibility to Pyelonephritis during Acute Hypertension by Vasoconstrictor Agents, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Effect of Angiotensin II on Renal Hypertensive Rats, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Effect of Diabetes on Pressor Responses to Noxious Stimuli, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Pyelonephritis and Hypertension: Experimental and Clinical Studies, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Social Determinants in the Use of Supportive Drugs, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Discussion - NKDF - 14th Annual Conference, Angiotensin Systems and Experimental Diseases, Undated (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Questions and Answers: Respiratory or Pharyngeal Infections and Pyelonephritis, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Questions and Answers: Pyelonephritis and Hypertension, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Comparison of Pathways of Pressor Response to Noxious Stimuli, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Editorial: Conference on Psychological Aspects of Cardiovascular Disease, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Catalase Test in the Detection of Urinary Infection in Hypertensive and Normotensive Patients, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - The Occurrence of Malignant Hypertension and Renal Insufficiency in Progressive Systemic Sclerosis (Diffuse Scleroderma), 1964 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Determinants of Cardiovascular Responsiveness to Ischemic Pain, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Timberline Conference Discussion, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Council for High Blood Pressure Research Discussion: Blood Pressure and Toxemia in Pregnancy, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - A Metabolic Change Secondary to Restraint, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Lipolytic Activity of Rat Adipose Tissue, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Evaluation of Antibiotics in Acute Pyelonephritis in Rats, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - A Lipolytic Activity of Rat Adipose Tissue, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - The Nature of Renal Involvement in Progressive Systemic Sclerosis (Scleroderma), 1965 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Diagnostic and Physiologic Implications of the Angiotensin Infusion Test, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Adrenergic Correlates to Pressor Responsivity, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Hyper-Responsivity to Angiotensin Induced in Rats by Stress, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Crout Discussion, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Renal Content of Renin-Like Material and Pressor Reactivity of Rats with Chronic Pyelonephritis, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Amphoteric Oxytetracycline in the Therapy of Experimental Acute Pyelonephritis in the Rat, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Effect of B-Blockage on Blood Pressure Reactivity and Its Adrenergic Correlates in Mild Hypertensives, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - An Analysis of the Variability of Blood Pressure, Pulse Rate, and Catecholamine Responsiveness to Noxious Stimuli in Identical and Fraternal Twins, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - B-Glucuronidase Excretion in Renal Homotransplant, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Renal Penetration of Insoluble and Soluble Tetracycline in Experimental Pyelonephritis, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Hemodynamic and Humoral Factors in Renal Electrolyte Cycles, Undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Psychophysiologic Considerations in Blood Pressure Responses, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Postural Effects on Renal Electrolyte Cycles, Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Double Blind Comparison of Ethacrynic Acid and Hydrochlorothiazide in Hypertension, Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - In Consultation, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Questions and Answers: Management of Benign Essential Hypertension, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Peripheral Renin Activity in Renal Parenchymal Disease with Hypertension, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Effect of High Sodium Intake on Blood Pressure of Rats with Experimental Pyelonephritis, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Mechanism of Nocturia in Primary Aldosteronism, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Indigotinuria: An Animal Model for the Blue-Diaper Syndrome?, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Hypoglycemia - Or Postural Hypertension?, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Perceptual Differences Between Hypertensive and Normotensive Persons, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Allopurinol use for Hyperuricemia in Hypertension, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Plasma Renin Variability with Hypertension and Severe Renal Insufficiency, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Development of Bacteriuria in a Hypertensive Population: A Seven Year Follow-up Study, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Plasma Renin Variability with Hypertension and Severe Renal Insufficiency, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - 2nd Annual Conference on Automated Indirect Blood Pressure - Panel Discussion, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Plasma Renin Activity (PRA) in Renal Failure with Hypertension, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Plasma Renin Activity (PRA) in Renal Failure with Hypertension [RESTRICTED], 1971 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Hypertension Control in the Community, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Council for High Blood Pressure Research: Discussion, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Discussion, Undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Study of a Third Year Surgical Clerkship: An Evaluation in Progress, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Blood Pressure and Heart Rate Response to Verbal Instruction and Relaxation in Hypertensives, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Conference of the Council for High Blood Pressure Research: Discussion, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Effect of Verbal Instruction and Relaxation on Blood Pressure Response and Recognition in Hypertensives, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Blood Pressure Regulation in Chronic Renal Failure of Polycystic Kidney Disease, Undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Letter to the Editor: Value of renal Differential Function Studies in Segmental Renal Ischemia, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Effects of Diving on Peripheral Venous Renin Activity in the Harbor Seal, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Discussion: Diuretic Drugs in the Treatment of Hypertension, Undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Minoxidil and the Management of Severe Hypertension - A Relationship to Renal Function, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Letter to the Editor: Hypertension and Unilateral Shrunken Kidney, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Letter to the Editor: Hypertension and Unilateral Shrunken Kidney [RESTRICTED], 1974 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Influence of Sodium Intake on Blood Pressure and the Renin-Angiotensin-Aldosterone System in Chronic Renal Failure of Polycystic Kidney Disease, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Book Review: Systemic Arterial Hypertension, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Anglo-American Conference on Continuing Medical Education: Proceedings, April 8-10, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Book Review, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Book Review, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Management of End-Stage Renal Failure Secondary to Progressive Systemic Sclerosis, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - End Stage Renal Failure Secondary to Scleroderma: Outcome of Treatment, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Renin in Scleroderma with Malignant Hypertension, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Letter to the Editor, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Plasma Renin Activity (PRA) in Progressive Systemic Sclerosis (Scleroderma) with Malignant Hypertension, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Beta-Adrenergic Blockade: A New Era in Cardiovascular Medicine: Symposium Discussion, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Book Review, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Questions and Answers: Unresponsive Hypertension in Middle-Aged Man, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Mild Hypertension Meeting: Discussion, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Effects of Chronic Diuretic Therapy on Cerebral Blood Flow (CBF) in Elderly Patients with Systolic Hypertension (SH), 1980 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Physician Approach to Controversial Issues in Hypertension, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Letter to the Editor, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Book Review, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Behavioral Consequences of Mild Hypertension, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Behavioral Consequences of Mild Hypertension, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 62)